<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-06-05T18:15:03+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Nick Buckets</title><subtitle>Tales from the Urban Inferno</subtitle><entry><title type="html">How long does it take to write a novel?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/visualizing-daily-word-count" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How long does it take to write a novel?" /><published>2024-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2024-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/visualizing-daily-word-count</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/visualizing-daily-word-count"><![CDATA[<p>Since Day 1 of my writing journey, I’ve been keeping track of the number of words I put down on 
paper each day. Reading around, I quickly realized that every author has their own pace.
Stephen King famously writes 2,500 words every single day – no exceptions. Ernest Hemingway was 
content with finishing his day with a fifth of that. Consistency is key, but for me, accepting 
my own writing pace and limits helped me become more productive. Oh, right. Gave me fewer
burnouts, too.</p>

<p>In the beginning, I used a simple table which I manually updated. A piece of paper won’t go a long
way if you plan to keep doing this, so any of the usual suspects (Google Sheets, Excel, 
LibreOffice, etc) will do. Recently I realized that the writing program which I use (Scrivener, 
not affiliated), automatically keeps track of this information. That was a fun moment, 
because I went back to my projects and began looking at the numbers. I knew how long each of my
books had taken me to write, but I didn’t know exactly how many days I wrote for each book, or
how many words.</p>

<p>There’s a common wisdom about word count when it comes to writing a book. Given that a novel has
about 90,000 words (depending on the genre), write 1,000 words per day and you’ve got yourself a 
first draft in as little as three months. Easy, right? If only. Here’s a 
visualization of the days I actually wrote for my second book, <em>Break Even</em>. These include only
days in which I progress the manuscript and exclude days in which I edit, revise, and proofread.</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src="/assets/images/blogpost_1_heatmap.png" alt="Visualization of daily word count for my second novel Break Even" style="width:600px" />
</p>

<p>Most of the days are gray, meaning I wrote exactly 0 words in these days. Zero. Zip. Nada.
There’s also a nice accumulation of writing happening around holidays, where I have more time
than usual. So, how many days did I <em>actually</em> write on?</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src="/assets/images/blogpost_1_distribution.png" alt="Distribution of daily word count for Break Even" style="width:600px" />
</p>

<p>97 days. With an average of 857 words per day, it took me exactly 97 days to type THE END in
my second novel. Of course I’m talking about a first draft which has to be improved, but hey,
this is what rewrites are for. The number 97 is strikingly close to the rule of thumb of 90 days.</p>

<p>The second thing the data shows me is the average number of words I write when I manage to write.
My daily average is about 850 words, and that’s what I feel comfortable with. Sure, I’ll have
good days where I crunch a couple of thousand words, but also days where I’ll struggle to 
come up with just a few hundred. The pattern I’ve noticed is the following though: a high day will
usually lead to a break the day after, while a low day not.</p>

<h3 id="okay-what-now">Okay, what now?</h3>
<p>I found that paying attention to the statistics of my daily word count helped my productivity.
I also found it fun to watch at.
Since I love data and visualization, I made this interactive app so that other writers can
explore their own statistics, learn something from the data, or just have fun plotting it.</p>

<h3 id="where">Where?</h3>
<p>The app is <a href="https://nickbuckets.shinyapps.io/word_count/">here</a>, and it looks like this:</p>

<p align="center">
  <img src="/assets/images/blogpost_1_viz_daily_word_count.png" alt="Interactive shiny app to visualize daily word count statistics" style="width:400px" />
</p>

<p>In case you want, you’ll be able to upload your own data and visualize it, as well as change the 
colors etc.</p>

<p>Enjoy!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="statistics" /><category term="visualization" /><category term="word count" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Since Day 1 of my writing journey, I’ve been keeping track of the number of words I put down on paper each day. Reading around, I quickly realized that every author has their own pace. Stephen King famously writes 2,500 words every single day – no exceptions. Ernest Hemingway was content with finishing his day with a fifth of that. Consistency is key, but for me, accepting my own writing pace and limits helped me become more productive. Oh, right. Gave me fewer burnouts, too.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Start here</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/welcome-to-the-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Start here" /><published>2023-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-12-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/welcome-to-the-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/welcome-to-the-blog"><![CDATA[<p>This is how my website looked like when I kicked-off this blog. In case you’re visiting it in the not so near future,
it hopefully looks richer than that.</p>

<h3 id="who">Who?</h3>

<p>Nick Buckets, crime fiction author. <a href="http://localhost:4000/#about">Have we already met?</a></p>

<h3 id="what">What?</h3>
<p>Stuff that doesn’t belong to a book, a collection of stories, or anything similar. These are mostly
ideas &amp; comments about reading &amp; writing, sometimes including data visualization, code etc.</p>

<h3 id="when">When?</h3>

<p>Here’s our contract: I’m going to post irregularly, most likely sparsely, and only when I feel I have
something to write down.</p>

<h3 id="where">Where?</h3>

<p>Right here.</p>

<h3 id="why">Why?</h3>

<p>I know what you’re thinking:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Writing books is already hard. Why start a blog on top of that?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Well, why not?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Because blogs are so out of fashion</p>
</blockquote>

<p>They are. But then again, so is everything else in life sooner or later, isn’t it?</p>

<h3 id="anything-else">Anything else?</h3>

<p>In case you arrived here from a search engine, feel free to navigate to my main page and check out 
my books.</p>

<p>Oh, and I love feedback. If you read any of my books, let me know how you liked them.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="uninformative" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to yet another blog]]></summary></entry></feed>